Guide to the Stanford University, Associate Provost for Computing, Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Associate Provost for Computing, records
1968-1971
SC0208
Miller, William F.
4.5 Linear feet
The records in this collection are the office files of Miller as Associate Provost for Computing (1968-70) and Vice President for Research (1970-71). Includes correspondence, memoranda, and proposals; subjects include SPIRES/BALLOTS, research policy, government agencies and research, computer science department, electrical engineering department, and health delivery systems.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer, 1981.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
William F. Miller, who holds three degrees in physics from Purdue University (B.S. 1949, M.S. 1951, Ph.D. 1956), joined Stanford in 1965 as a professor of computer science. He was also appointed professor and head of the computation group at the Stanford Linear Acceleration Center in 1965. In 1968 he was named associate provost for computing and in 1970 he became the first vice president for research. From 1971 to 1978 he was vice president and provost of the university.
During that period he directed the development of the budget equilibrium program, widely regarded as an outstanding model for resource planning and management in academic institutions. He was personally active in the development of several new teaching and research programs and played a key role in the five-year $300 million "Campaign for Stanford" capital drive.
Miller led Stanford delegations to the People's Republic of China in 1976 and 1978 and was the principal university officer in negotiation of student and scholarly exchanges with that nation. In 1979 he became the first Herbert Hoover professor of public and private management in the Graduate School of Business, before being named president and cief executive officer of SRI International. He has served on the National Acdemy of Sciences' Computer Science and Engineering Board and on the National Research Council's Committee on Graduate and Postdoctoral Education since 1968.
Description of the Collection
The records in this collection are the office files of Miller as Associate Provost for Computing (1968-70) and Vice President for Research (1970-71). Includes correspondence, memoranda, and proposals; subjects include SPIRES/BALLOTS, research policy, government agencies and research, computer science department, electrical engineering department, and health delivery systems.
Access Terms
BALLOTS Project.; Miller, William F.; Stanford University. Associate Provost for Computing.; Stanford University. Computer Science Department.; Stanford University. Department of Electrical Engineering.; Stanford University. Office of Vice President for Research.; Universities and colleges--Data processing.; Universities and colleges--Research.
Collection Contents
- Papers, 1968-1971
  - National Center for Atmospheric Research, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - BALLOTS/SPIRES merger (5100), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - SPIRES/BALLOTS Executive Advisory Committee (5200), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - SPIRES/BALLOTS space (5400), undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Technical matters (5300), undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Texas Instruments, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - SPIRES/BALLOTS budgets (5500), undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Academic Freedoms and Research Controls, by Joseph D. Sneed, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - WFM Correspondence, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Floyd promotion, complete 7/10/70, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Federal Aviation Administration (6600), undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - US Department of Labor (6700), undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - OST - Carl York (6810), undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Other Government agencies (6900), undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - US Department of Housing and Urban Development (6920), undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Environmental Protection Agency (6930), undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Research policy - general (8001), undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Research policy - general (8001), undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Type C consultancies, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - University Research Policy 1969 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Grant foundations (9500), undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Nondiscriminatory hiring (9505), undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Reduction of staff (9600), undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - University policy - general (9000), undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - University organization (9200), undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - University stance on political action (Lyman memo) (9100), undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Travel policy (9300), undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Research administration (8150), undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Government property control (8151), undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - SPIRES (NSF grant) - general (5600), undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Standard computer, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - US Atomic Energy Commission (6100), undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Bureau of the budget (6150), undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Qualifying exams, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Social science computing, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Computers - general, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Computers - general, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - SLAC, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Graphic processing, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Computer science building, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Proposals, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Proposals, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - University of Nevada consulting, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Computer science department, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Stanford computing forum, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Computer science department, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Hewlett-Packard, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Computer science department research, source of support, etc., undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Electrical engineering department computer program, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Computer science department appointments, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Computer science Ph.D students, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Special interest group on computer science education, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Artificial intelligence project, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "Technology and Man", undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence - miscellaneous, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Health delivery systems, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Health delivery systems - regional medical program, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Multidisciplinary health services research, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Washington State University (Richard), May 22nd, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Cornell computing, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Provost funds, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Allocation of University computer funds (responses), undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - University computing funds, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Computer Science department - general correspondence, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Provost funds, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Stanford Computing Company, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Patrick audit (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - ACME Facility (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Summary of financial status -- SCC (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - SCC campus facility operations, etc., undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Davier/Bloom appointments - SIAC, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - W. K. H. Panofsky - Director of SIAC, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Microprogramming research in the computation group systems lab, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Provost - computing affairs, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Computer acquisitions, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Provost - computing affairs, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)